<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A briefe and true declaration of the sicknesse, last wordes, and death of the King of Spaine Philip the second of that name who died in his Abbey of S. Laurence at Escuriall seuen miles from Madrill the 13. of September 1598. Written from Madrill in a Spanish letter, and translated into English according to the true copie.</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1599</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 11 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 7 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-04">2011-04 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A09554</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 19833.5</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S110449</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99845989</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99845989</idno>
            <idno type="VID">10924</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A09554)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 10924)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 1668:4)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A briefe and true declaration of the sicknesse, last wordes, and death of the King of Spaine Philip the second of that name who died in his Abbey of S. Laurence at Escuriall seuen miles from Madrill the 13. of September 1598. Written from Madrill in a Spanish letter, and translated into English according to the true copie.</title>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[12] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>By Edm. Bollifant, for William Aspley,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>Printed at London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1599.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Signatures: A-B⁴ (-A1, B4).</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Philip --  II, --  King of Spain, 1527-1598.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2009-12</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-12</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-02</date>
            <label>Mona Logarbo</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-02</date>
            <label>Mona Logarbo</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-04</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:10924:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <!-- PDF PAGE 57 -->
            <p>A BRIEFE AND TRVE Declaration of the ſickneſſe, laſt <hi>wordes, and death of the King of Spaine</hi> PHILIP the ſecond of that name, who died in his Abbey of S. Laurence at Eſcuriall ſeuen miles from Madrill the 13. of September 1598.</p>
            <p>Written from Madrill in a Spaniſh letter, and tranſlated into Engliſh accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding <hi>to the true Copie.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Printed at London by Edm. Bollifant,</hi> for William Aſpley. 1599</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:10924:2"/>
            <!-- PDF PAGE 58 -->
            <pb facs="tcp:10924:2"/>
            <!-- PDF PAGE 58 -->
            <head>A briefe and true declaration of the <hi>ſickneſſe, last wordes, and death of the</hi> King of Spaine PHILIP the ſecond of that name, who died in his Abbey of S. Laurence <hi>at Eſcuriall, ſeauen miles from Madrill, the 13. of September</hi> 1598.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>O ſatisfie my promiſe, and to giue anſwere to your letters, requiring my aduertiſement of theſe preſent occurrences, I pray you vnderſtand, that this yeere 1598. the Royall Maieſtie of our Lord Don PHILIP the third, being then but Prince, was vpon S. Iohns day, in the market place at Madrill, to beholde the Bullbaytings and other paſtymes which were there, at which ſports the King his father (which is now in heauen) was not preſent by reaſon of the paine of the gout which ſore troubled him. His Highnes being returned from the foreſaid place, diſcourſed vnto his father all that he had ſeene, whereupon his Maieſtie anſwered, I am
<pb facs="tcp:10924:3"/>
               <!-- PDF PAGE 59 -->right glad to ſee thee ſo pleaſant, for thou ſhalt neuer ſo long as I liue ſee me haue any eaſe or comfort in this my painfull diſeaſe. And there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>upon commaunded preparation to be made for his remouing to Eſcuriall. Doctor Marcado one of his ordinarie Phiſitions tolde him, he ought not to ſtirre, leaſt the extremitie of his paine ſhould increaſe. The King anſwered, ſee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing I muſt be carried thither when I am dead, I had rather be carried thither being aliue. So that in the end to ſatisfie his deſire, his footmen tooke him vp vpon their ſhoulders, &amp; ſpent ſixe daies in going thoſe ſeauen miles, where after that he came, he was better for ſome few daies, though he was not able to ſtand, but was for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced either to ſit or lie. But preſently the goute reſeaſing him, accompanied with a feuer, made him far ſicker then he was before, his Phiſitions ſhewed all the skil they could to giue him ſome eaſe, but the extremitie of paine ſo increaſed, that preſently he entred into conſideration of his ſoule by ſhriuing and confeſſing himſelfe, and receiuing the ſacrament, at which inſtant he commanded Garcia de Loyaza to be con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſecrated
<pb facs="tcp:10924:3"/>
               <!-- PDF PAGE 59 -->Archbiſhop of Toledo, which was per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formed by the Popes Nuntio with all the ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lemnities and rites accuſtomed. There happe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned alſo to this good King vpon his right knee, a bile ſo angrie and ſwelling, that he could take no reſt, his Phiſitions being amazed thereat, one Elias a Phiſition of Toledo, by whoſe ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uice and direction of others, one Vergara a licentiate Surgeon hauing applied al fit meanes to ripen the ſore, opened it, and let foorth all the bad matter therein contained: ſoone after the which, there aroſe fower other biles vpon his breſt, which likewiſe were ripened, opened and cleanſed. This corrupt matter bred a great companie of lice, which were very hard to bee killed, he remaining in this mean time ſo weake that he was faine to be turned in ſheetes, and lift vp with fower men, whileſt two other made all things plaine, ſoft, and cleane vnder him. Ten daies before he died, he fell into ſo great a traunce (laſting fiue howers) that it was eaſily perceiued, that his life and vitall powers began to faile, which cauſed diuers Lords in Madrill to prouide mourning garments. Being retur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned
<pb facs="tcp:10924:4"/>
               <!-- PDF PAGE 60 -->to himſelfe, he ſaid to the Archbiſhop and to thoſe of the chamber there preſent: My friends and ſubiects, your ſorrowes are of no force to recouer my health, for no humane re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>medie can profit me. The chiefe matter of your care ought to be to prouide in time all neceſſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries for my funerals, and in the meane time I commaunde you to call hither your Prince, which ſhall be your future King, and fetch hi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther vnto me my coffin that I ſhall be laide in, and place here vpon this little cupboord, a dead mans skull crowned with my imperiall crowne, all which was foorthwith done. The Prince and the Infanta his ſiſter being in preſence, the King called for Iohn Ruyz de Valaſco, putting him in minde of a cofer which he had committed to his cuſtodie, willing him to fetch it, the cofer was very little, yet when it was brought he cau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed it to be opened, and taking foorth a preti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous ſtone of an infinite value, cauſed it to be deliuered to his Daughter, ſpeaking thus vnto hir. My daughter Izabella Eugenia Clara, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiue this Iewell brought vnto me by your mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, the which I beſtowe vpon you for my laſt
<pb facs="tcp:10924:4"/>
               <!-- PDF PAGE 60 -->farewell. And then turning him to the Prince, ſaid, are you contented with this that I giue vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to your ſiſter? Who anſwered, yea ſir, although you gaue her all that I haue. This anſwere ly<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king the King very wel, he willed them to looke in the cofer for an other paper, and giuing it to the Prince, he tolde him, that therein he ſhould ſee the forme how to gouerne his kingdome. Then they tooke out of the ſaid cofer, a whip with bloudie knots, which the King holding vp ſaid, This bloud is mine owne, and yet not mine but my fathers, who is in heauen, who made vſe of this kinde of exerciſe, and therefore to make knowne the value of it, and the trueth of it I thought good to reueale it vnto you. After this he commaunded a paper to be taken from vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der his pillow, which being read by Iohn Ruyz, contained theſe words. We PHILIP by the grace of God, King of Caſtile and Lion &amp;c. hauing gouerned this Realme 40. yeeres, in the 71. yeeres of mine age, giue ouer this King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome vnto my God to whome it belongeth, and commend my ſoule into his bleſſed hands, to performe therewith whatſoeuer it ſhal pleaſe
<pb facs="tcp:10924:5"/>
               <!-- PDF PAGE 61 -->his diuine Maieſtie. Commaunding that this my bodie ſo ſoone as euer my ſoule ſhall bee ſeparated from the ſame, be embalmed: then apparelled with a Royall robe, and ſo placed in this brazen ſhrine heere preſent, and that the howers be kept, with all rites and ceremonies as the lawe requireth, and I commaund my fu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerals to be ſolemnized in this manner. Before ſhall be borne the Archbiſhops banner, then the Croſſe, the Monkes and the Clergie pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſently ſhall followe, all in mourning garments. The Adelantado ſhall beare the Royall ſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dard trailing it vpon the ground.<note place="margin">Adelantado is the Admi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall of the Gallies.</note> The Duke of Nayara ſhall carrie the crowne vnder a cano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pie. The Marqueſſe of Aguillar ſhall carrie the ſword. My body ſhall be borne by eight of my chiefeſt ſeruants all in mourning weedes, with burning torches in their handes. The Archbi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhop ſhall follow the Nobles, and our vniuerſal Heire ſhall follow on the one ſide all in dewle. When they come to the Church, my body ſhal be placed in the herſe there of purpoſe erected. All the praiers and deuotions ended, the Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>late ſhall place me in the vault, my laſt habita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion
<pb facs="tcp:10924:5"/>
               <!-- PDF PAGE 61 -->which ſhall be giuen to me foreuer. All this performed, your Prince, and third King of that name, ſhall goe to S. Ieroſmes at Madrill there to keep the holy ceremonies of the ninth day yeerely, and my Daughter with my ſiſter her Aunt ſhall goe to the gray Nunnes bare<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>foote. Then ſpeaking to the Prince he ſaide, beſides all that which I haue heertofore ſpoken to you, I pray you haue a great care and regard to your ſiſter, becauſe ſhee was my looking glaſſe &amp; the light of mine eies. Keepe the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon wealth in peace, placing there good go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uernors to rewarde the good and puniſh the bad. Let the Marqueſſe of Mondeiar be deli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uered out of priſon, on this condition that he come not to the Court. Let the wife of Antonio Perez alſo be ſet at libertie, ſo that from hence<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>foorth ſhee liue in a monaſterie, and let her daughters inherite the patrimonie which ſhee brought. Forgiue thoſe which are priſoners for hunting, with all ſuch as are condemned to die, (the Kings pardon wanting) and ſo I giue my laſt farewell to my children, commending them to all peace and ſafetie. Then the Prince asked
<pb facs="tcp:10924:6"/>
               <!-- PDF PAGE 62 -->Don Chriſtofer de Mora for the Royall Key, commaunding him to deliuer it to him, who craued pardon of his Highnes, becauſe it was the Key of all truſt and confidence, which hee could in no wiſe deliuer without the leaue of his Lord the King. Well, ſaid the Prince, it is ynough. And ſo went into his chamber, whileſt Don Chriſtofer returning to the King, whome he found a little cheered, ſaid vnto him. Sir, his Highnes asked of me the Royall Key, which I haue denied him as hauing no leaue from your Maieſtie. But the King told him he had done ill. Not long after he fell into another fit, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>upon he called for the extreme vnction, which was giuen vnto him by the Archbiſhop. Then he called for a Crucifixe which had beene kept ſafely in a cheſt, which was the very ſame his father held betweene his hands, when he died, with the which he deſired likewiſe to die. Here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>upon his Highnes returned to his father, at whoſe comming Don Chriſtofer vppon his knees preſented to him the Royall Key, which the Prince receiued, and gaue it to the Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>queſſe of Denia: whereupon the King ſaide to
<pb facs="tcp:10924:6"/>
               <!-- PDF PAGE 62 -->him. Remember I commend vnto you Don Chriſtofer for the moſt faithfull ſeruant which I euer had, and ſo haue care of al the reſt, which I commende vnto you. And ſo he tooke his leaue of him againe imbracing him, at which inſtant his ſpeech failed. And in this ſort hee continued two daies, and died vpon Sunday the 13. of September about three of the clocke in the morning. The body was buried vpon Munday the 14. of that moneth, about nine of the clocke in the morning, the Archbiſhop ſay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the maſſe. The new King came from Eſcu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riall the 16. of that inſtant, leauing his ſiſter at the gray Nunnes, and ſo went to S. Ieroſmes, the Court remaining in great mourning and lamentation, making prepa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration for the great funerall.</p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            <pb facs="tcp:10924:7" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <!-- PDF PAGE 63 -->
            <pb facs="tcp:10924:7"/>
            <!-- PDF PAGE 63 -->
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
